<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Morall obseruations By W.W. Gent.</title>
            <author>Wynne, William, fl. 1616-1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15799</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26060</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102798</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838560</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838560</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2942</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15799)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2942)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1125:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Morall obseruations By W.W. Gent.</title>
                  <author>Wynne, William, fl. 1616-1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[38] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edw: Allde, and are to be sold at his house ioyning to Christ-Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>W.W. = William Wynne.</note>
                  <note>Allde was the printer as well as the bookseller--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A(-A1) B C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ethics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2942:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2942:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MORALL Obſeruations.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W.W.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Edw: Allde,</hi> and are to be ſold at his houſe ioyning to Chriſt-Church. 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2942:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2942:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST HOPE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full light of true Nobility, <hi>the right honorable</hi> Iames <hi>Lord</hi> Matreuers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT honorable, the increaſe of yeares in mans life, hath the best compariſon to the ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding perfections of the worlds age: Wherein (if reuelations, and reuealed teachings be excepted) wee finde by obſeruation of Hiſtorie deriued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, a waxing, and waining in all Arts and actions: A breeding, an infancie, a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlines, a perfection and ſtate, and then a
<pb facs="tcp:2942:3"/>d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>clyning, ſo that ſuch inſpection of the worlds ſtorye, is a fit repreſentation to be conſidered for the formatiue trayning of our particulariti<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s from the firſt, and weakeſt capacitie of inſtruction, to the laſt and ſtrongeſt abilitie of performance: which will produce the beſt, and moſt enabled endurance of vnderſtanding vigor in the declining yeares: which though natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally they breede decay in ſtrength, and power of naturall functions, yet with ſuch Cuſtome of vſe, in the long and conſtant exerciſe of a vertuous minde, cannot want ſufficiencie of all poſsible ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that may be expected from the true groundes of a well tempered vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Thoſe things wh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch full yeares hauing attayned can teach others, are not fit to be preſented vnto ſuch yeares, but ſerue as fruites allready rypened, to be layed, and kept in ſtore, at ſeaſonable times to be beſtowed on children and younger yeares. Such be theſe obſeruations, which I preſent to your honor, deſiring therein nothing
<pb facs="tcp:2942:3"/>more, then the commending of ready will to doe all honeſt and ſeruiceable duties to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors humbly to be commaunded <hi>William Wynne.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proverbs">
            <pb facs="tcp:2942:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2942:4"/>
            <head>Morall Obſeruations.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Tyme, bookes, and reading.</head>
               <p>AMong all things precious, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more precious, nor any thing ſo much ours, as <hi>Tyme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2 Euery houre is to be embraced in our armes; for he, that hath his hand in to-day, ſhall the leſſe care for to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrow.</p>
               <p>3 The firſt ſigne of a well compoſed minde, is to ſettle with it ſelfe, or to ſtay at home. <q xml:lang="lat">Secum morari.</q> 
                  <bibl>Sen:</bibl>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2942:5"/>
               <p> 4 The turning ouer of diuers volumes together, breedes confuſion; it taſtes ſomewhat of a wandering and vnſtable diſpoſition. <q xml:lang="lat">Nuſqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, qui vbi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p> 5 Who runnes thus on Pilgrimage, meetes with many Innes, and fewe friends; he ſees much, and learnes little.</p>
               <p>6 Nothing more offenciue to health, then variety of remedies; A Plant of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tranſplanted, ſeldome proſpers; and a multitude of bookes, diſtract the minde.</p>
               <p> 7 Read choyce, and approued Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors; and when you growe wearie, leaue, and retyre to the ſame againe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2942:5"/>
               <p> 8 Though we cannot read all we haue, yet (which is better) let vs haue all wee read.</p>
               <p>9 In much reading, ſomthing will offer it ſelfe to your obſeruation, vſe, or ſeruice; Let not that ſlippe indige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, or till meditation haue made it your owne.</p>
               <p>10 Somtimes, it is not amis, with <hi>Seneca</hi> to viſit the tents of ſtrangers, yet not as a fugitiue, but as an intelligencer.</p>
               <p>11 The vſe of bookes is to be lymitted, as the vſe of meates, according to the quality of the vſer; for in all things, what is too little for one may ouerlaye another; Theref<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re, the beſt is, not to deſire aboundance, but enough, this is alwayes profitable, yet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<q xml:lang="lat">
                     <pb facs="tcp:2942:6"/>hurtfull. Omne nimiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vertitur in vitiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Choyſe of a Friend.</head>
               <p>VVHen you eſteeme any to be your friend, whome you dare not truſt as your ſelfe; you may thinke you are therein deceaued, as not diſcerning betwixt an acquaintance and a friend, or not well vnderſtanding the nature, and power of friendſhip.</p>
               <p>2 A man full of imployment, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, can haue no greater miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, then to repute thoſe for his friends, to whome he is no friend himſelfe.</p>
               <p>3 Before friendſhippe conſider, after friendſhip truſt.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2942:6"/>
               <p> 4 I ſay conſider long before you admit any to be your friend, but once being admitted, entertaine him in your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, lodge him in your heart, and talke with him, as with your ſelfe.</p>
               <p>5 Some there are, who to euery one they meet, will vtter what they ſhould onely impart to their friends, and tell all they feele itching in their owne eares; others againe are ſo ſcrupulous, that the honeſt conſcience of their dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt friend, is not worthy of their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret; and if it were poſſible, they would conceale it from themſelues. Neither of theſe, is to be liked; for it is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall fault, to truſt all, and to truſt none.
<q xml:lang="lat">Vtrum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vitiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, et omnibus credere, &amp; nulli.</q>
               </p>
               <p>6 Conſult freely with your friend of
<pb facs="tcp:2942:7"/>all things, but firſt of your ſelfe.</p>
               <p>7 True friends will ſtand faſt in aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie; they will loue, and frequent thoſe moſte that of Fortune are moſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken.
<q xml:lang="lat">Amicus certus, in re incerta cernitur.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Wit and Memorie.</head>
               <p>I Had rather haue a good, then an excellent wit, for that will not ſtoop to vildneſſe, and this is flexible to any thing.</p>
               <p>2 Great faults haue ſeldome iſſued, but from great wits.</p>
               <p>3 A great Memorie, is a large ſtoare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe,
<pb facs="tcp:2942:7"/>full of blacke ſmoaky imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and yrkeſome toyles.</p>
               <p>4 In the remembrance of many things, few yeeld contentment; many vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and oft times, the very delights thereof are troubleſome.</p>
               <p>5 Of all other, the remembrance of an ill name, is moſt heauy and ſadde, euen in the middeſt of all honor; ſo tender, delicate, and incurable aboue whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer els, is <hi>Fame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>6 Great moleſtation, is the inſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Companion of great memorie; for ſome matters remembred ſting the Conſcience: ſome wound it; other terrifie, and vtterly confound it.</p>
               <p>7 But why doe ſo many boaſt of their Memorie, and yet forget both the
<pb facs="tcp:2942:8"/>
                  <hi>Tyme,</hi> and themſelues.</p>
               <p>8 All erre in this; that they deſire to learne things worthie to be forgotten, and forget what is fit to be learn'd.</p>
               <p>9 Will you knowe the beſt memorie? then obſerue this; remember your ſin, that you may be ſorry: remember your Death, that you may forbeare: remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Gods iuſtice, that you may feare: remember his mercy, that you may not diſpaire.
<q xml:lang="lat">Quid memoriam jactas? vnde haec obliuio diei vnius? vnde tui ipſius?</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertue.</head>
               <p>THe nature of vertue, is to attend, not ſo much what ſhe hath done, as
<pb facs="tcp:2942:8"/>what ſhee is yet to doe; not ſo much what ſhe enioyeth, as what ſhe wanteth; from whence it is that ſhee gloryes not in what ſhee hath, but is ſollicitous about that ſhe hath not.</p>
               <p>2. Me thinks, if (it were lawfull) I could ſay, Vertue is couetous, or much like to Auarice; For ſhee continually thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, burneth, longeth: the more ſhee ſeekes, and findes, the poorer ſhee ſeemes, hauing no meane in her deſires; and worthely: For indeed, the heape of true honour, and merrit, can neuer be too great.</p>
               <p>3. Vertue is no Braggard, no admirer of her ſelfe, but an humble follower of others; And when ſhee aſpires and ſits higheſt, then ſhe reckons her ſelfe leaſt.</p>
               <p>4. Vertue knowes this to be the time of
<pb facs="tcp:2942:9"/>warfare, not of triumph; Therefore ſhee is euer watching, euer in action.
<q xml:lang="lat">Virtus p<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>it et in actione, la<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſs<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> proficis.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Opinion.</head>
               <p>WHo thinkes hee is arriued to the point, or height of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, is firſt deceiued in this; That hee beleeued himſelfe to be, where he is not; next he forſakes the right way by going wrong; and by anticipating what hee hath not, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly preuents, what he might haue had.</p>
               <p>2. There is no ſuch Aduerſary, or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance to the purſuite of vertue, as the opinion of perfection; For who will
<pb facs="tcp:2942:9"/>labour for that which hee thinkes fit hath already?</p>
               <p>3. If I haue any thing in me that is good, I knowe from whome it comes, and I am glad; If I want any thing, I knowe of whome to aske, and of him will I hope for it.</p>
               <p>4. Opinion alters no matter, no lawes, no effect.</p>
               <p>5. Vaine hopers, and louers, are like wiſhers and woulders, all ſelfe-decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and neuer to be truſted.</p>
               <p>6. What if my Neighbours magnifie my name? May not each of them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue another, and all deceiue me?</p>
               <p>7. The Cittyes, or Townes acclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſhould neuer make me thinke the
<pb facs="tcp:2942:10"/>better of my ſelfe; For in my inward ſoule, there is a more certaine, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupt witneſſe of me; my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; Shee will tell me true, and I will truſt her.</p>
               <p>8. Opinion is but a certaine name, to an vncertaine matter.</p>
               <p>9. Hee that is good in his owne opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; is ſtarke naught in very deede; For good men are with none ſo much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed, as with themſelues.</p>
               <p>10. But I ſeeme not good to my ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but to others alſo: Yet what if I be naught and thoſe other Fooles?</p>
               <p>11. It is ill to deceiue others, but worſe to deceiue your ſelfe.</p>
               <p>12. Why, but all men ſpeake well of me;
<pb facs="tcp:2942:10"/>Oh ioyfull newes; But ſhall I be ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, as to beleeue all men? <q xml:lang="lat">Opiniorem non mutat.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Vulgar Example.</head>
               <p>THere is no knowne way ſo ready, and headlong to errour, as by the example and ſteps of the vulgar.</p>
               <p>2 To pleaſe the vulgar, is to diſpleaſe God.</p>
               <p>3 Who layes vp his hopes, or ſettles his praiſes in the Common people, is like him, that ſets withered plants, in barren plots.</p>
               <p>4 Whatſoeuer the vulgar thinkes, is vncertaine:
<q>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2942:11"/>
                     <l>Whatſoeuer it ſpeakes is falſe,</l>
                     <l>Whatſoeuer it blames, is good,</l>
                     <l>Whatſoeuer it allowes is naught:</l>
                     <l>Whatſoeuer it praiſes, is infamous,</l>
                     <l>Whatſoeuer it doth, is fooliſh.</l>
                  </q>
                  <q xml:lang="lat">Qui vulgi latratus ferre didicit, nullos horrebit Canes.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Lybertie.</head>
               <p>NOt he that is borne, is free, but he that is buryed; for ouer the firſt, Fortune hath great power, ouer the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter none at all.</p>
               <p>2 We muſt not thinke our ſelues free becauſe we are without Lord or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: for wee cannot bee ignorant, at what yeares <hi>Hecuba,</hi> and <hi>Creſus</hi> began to ſerue.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2942:11"/>
               <p> 3 Let no man ſwell with his freedome, and liberty; for not onely free men, but Kings haue beene brought to thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p>4 Vnworthy reſtraynt, is better then vnworthy liberty.</p>
               <p>5 No reſtraint ſo ſtrict, no poyſon ſo noyſome, as the Cage of our owne Carcaſſe; in which yet we loue to liue, as fearefull, and loath to be rid out.</p>
               <p>6 Others write bookes in priſon, and you vtter bootleſſe ſighes, and teares; others gett knowledge, and will you forget patience?</p>
               <p>7 Many for the loue of God, or hatred of the world, or ſome other good end, haue choſen to liue in Caues, and
<pb facs="tcp:2942:12"/>holes: and if I cannot be of that minde but that I would faine be free, I muſt expect, till Man or Death, (who keepes an other Key) worke my deliuery.</p>
               <p>8 Moſt Priſons haue but one way in, and many wayes out: mercy deliuers ſome, Iuſtice others, Innocency others; ſome get out by wit, ſome by money; ſome by the honeſt Keepers negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, ſome by fauour of the night; (an Earth-quake may happen, to ſhake downe the walls) and others whom no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els can help, Death will deliuer.</p>
               <p>9 Priſons haue ſent fome forth to their greater glory, others to excellent For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, many to heauen, and all to their graues: to conclude, they receiue none, whom they render not againe.
<q xml:lang="lat">Quibuſdem, omnis vita ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicium viſa eſt.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:2942:12"/>
               <head>Praiſe of Natiue Soyle.</head>
               <p>LIttle auailes it any man to be borne in a famous ſoyle, vnles he harbour vertue, and hate vice in himſelfe.</p>
               <p>2 The chiefe praiſe of any Country, is the vertue of the men.</p>
               <p>3 <hi>Cataline</hi> had not beene ſo infamous, but that his Country was ſo famous.</p>
               <p>4 The eminency of a great, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Citty, holds many obſcure, and of ſmall account, whom the obſcurity, of a bare-country-Village, would haue made eminent, and of much repute.</p>
               <p>5 Your Country will be ſure to chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge
<pb facs="tcp:2942:13"/>its owne praiſe, and participate with yours, for whatſoeuer you doe nobly, or well, is in manner, your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes praiſe firſt, and yours after.</p>
               <p>6 <hi>Plato</hi> thank'd, and praiſd Nature; firſt for making him a reaſonable creature, and not a meere Animall; a man, and not a woman; a <hi>Grecian,</hi> not a <hi>Barbarian;</hi> an <hi>Athenian,</hi> not a <hi>Theban;</hi> and laſtly, for being borne in <hi>Socrates</hi> time, of whome he might receaue the further benefit of inſtruction and learning.
<q xml:lang="lat">Nihil aeque Ciuitates amplificat, vt Ciuium virtus, ac gloria.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Noble decent, praiſe, glory.</head>
               <p>THe merits of noble and worthy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, are markes to degenerate Children, nothing more detecting the
<pb facs="tcp:2942:13"/>poſterities vice, then the Parents ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</p>
               <p>2 The vertue of one, may, and doth often help, and profit another, but if you raiſe not glory, and praiſe for your ſelfe, neuer expect them from an other.</p>
               <p>3 The father may loue his ſonne, and leaue him his land, but neuer make him laudable: hence it is, that oft times an infinite ecclips of the fathers light, is ſuffred in the ſonne.</p>
               <p>4 The ſhining glory of Anceſtors, is good in this, that the poſterity cannot liue hidden, though it would.</p>
               <p>5 Glory is not gotten by noble birth, but by noble life; yea, (which is admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) often by Death.
<q xml:lang="lat">Nobilis non naſcitur, ſed fit.</q>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2942:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2942:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:2942:15"/>
               <head>Imitation.</head>
               <p>THe Imitation of great perſons, is neither ſafe, nor neceſſarie for all men: euery feathered Foule cannot ſoar after the Eagle: ſome Imitators, will doe cleaue contrary; others, another thing; others, the ſame thing an other way; and few will Imitate to the full, as their example did lead them.</p>
               <p>2 I know not how it falls out, that the vertues of our owne lyne, are leſſe imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to our ſelues, then to others; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be, that vertue will not ſeeme hereditary: I ſpeake faintly, but the thing it ſelfe ſpeakes freely; The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſonne, of an excellent Father is rarely ſeene.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Raro excellentis viri, filius excellens fuit.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:2942:15"/>
               <head>Comportment.</head>
               <p>WHatſoeuer you doe, ſo doe it as if your enemies ſtood by.</p>
               <p>2 That comportment is much better, that makes your Enemies admire you, then inuites your friends to excuſe you; and cleerer is that Fame, againſt which none can obiect truly, nor dares falſly, then that, which is once touch't, and then purged. <q xml:lang="lat">Talis post exitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fama eſt, qualis ante exitum vita.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Dyce-play.</head>
               <p>DYce-play: oh vnſatiable, and huge deuourer; ſad, and ſudden waſter
<pb facs="tcp:2942:16"/>of Patrymonyes; mindes fury, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbation; <hi>Fames</hi> obſcurity, ſpurre of ſinne, and path of deſperation.</p>
               <p>2 No proſperous end of Dyce-play, but all naught, all miſerable; for both the looſer is afflicted, and the winner entrapped.</p>
               <p>3 What if you haue played, and woon? may you not play againe and looſe?</p>
               <p>4 What you haue woon, a thouſand are watching to get from you, and that you haue loſt, none will reſtore to you.</p>
               <p>5 How many ſtrange things haue wee ſeene done by very valiant, and worthy men at play, for a little money, which at other times, and places, the ſame men, would not haue done, for any earthly treaſure? But there, is the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="tcp:2942:16"/>where all vice raignes; eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Auarice, and Anger.</p>
               <p>6 <hi>Luſi, vici, gaudio;</hi> I haue played, I haue woon, and now I reioyce: Oh impure play, oh damnable gaine: oh vaine ioy.</p>
               <p>7 Let this ſuffice; that all gladnes in our owne hurt, is madneſſe; all ioye in the ſame, meere folly.
<q xml:lang="lat">Omne de ſuo malo gaudium, ſtultum eſt.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Stage-playes and Players.</head>
               <p>PLayers moue me to laugh; but what doe you moue them to? How often hath the Player laught in his ſleeue at his beſt ſpectator, for laughing at him? how often muſing at the mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:2942:17"/>of his admyrers, hath he ſeyned that, whereby, he hath falſely pleaſed them, and truly pleaſed himſelfe?</p>
               <p>2 He that entertaines Players, hath whereat to laugh, and as hartily to be laugh'd at, yea, and whereby, to be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vp.
<q xml:lang="lat">Qui te rideant, &amp; rodant.</q>
               </p>
               <p>3 It is a conſequent; that who findes taſte in what's ill, is euer ignorant in that's good; nor in truth, can they be acquainted with noble actions, that are taken with vile, and baſe pleaſures.</p>
               <p>4 Who delights to ſee Playes, delights to ſee that, which can neither be honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewen, nor honeſtly ſeene, and hard it is to ſay, whether the Actor, or ſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tator be more infamous; the Stage, or the Stewes, the one being drawne with
<pb facs="tcp:2942:17"/>beggery, the other with vanity.</p>
               <p>5 Many, whom <hi>Nature</hi> had framed gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and milde, Playes haue made fierce, and cruell: mans minde prone to vice, ſhould rather be bridled, then vrged; for though it be left to it ſelfe, it hardly ſtayes, but being driuen, it runnes head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, after the olde Age, They muſt needs goe, whom the Deuill driues.</p>
               <p>6 Many miſchiefes are conuayed by the eates, but many more by the eyes; for at the eyes, as at two open windowes, <hi>Death</hi> breaks in with violence, to the ſoule; The memory takes no impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo powerfully, as by the eyes; or eares often, and lightly let in, and let out againe; but what wee ſee, (vnleſſe we ſee vnwillingly) ſticketh faſt: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then doe you goe? or what fury hales you on to Playes? where you may
<pb facs="tcp:2942:18"/>be pleaſed for an houre, and diſpleaſed for euer; where you ſhall ſee that once, which a thouſand times, you will wiſh, you had neuer ſeen.</p>
               <p>7 The Fame, and reputation of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, haue been left, and loſt at pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique ſpectacles, and Playes; many haue returnd bold, and wanton from them; many, and many againe doubtfull, and wauering: But chaſter, and ſoberer then they went, none,
<q xml:lang="lat">Acies Hiſtrionum, eſt ſicut Muſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quae vnctu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> comitantur, ſiccum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> deſtituant.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Wiſdome, Fortune, Folly.</head>
               <p>WIſdome, and Fortune, rarely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree well together.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2942:18"/>
               <p> 2 <hi>Fortune</hi> tells you, you are wiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you are wealthy; and makes you bold to ſay ſo: oh but heare, &amp; beleeue Reaſon; if it were ſo indeed, you would neuer ſay ſo.</p>
               <p>3 Things would goe well, if there were as many wiſe men, as profeſſors of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p>4 The firſt degree of a foole, is to thinke himſelfe wiſe; the next, to ſay ſo.</p>
               <p>5 Not to wiſh for that we cannot haue, but well to vſe what we haue, is true wiſdome: the firſt is common, the latter rare.
<q xml:lang="lat">
                     <l>Sapientia, bonorum rector eſt, malo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum victor.</l>
                     <l>Facere docet philoſophia, non di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:2942:19"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icinitie, and Enmitie.</head>
               <p>IT is commonly ſeene, that where is neereſt <hi>vicinity</hi> of houſes, there is fartheſt diſtance of hearts: Nere neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, are ſeeldom free from iarres, and quarrells.</p>
               <p>2 Many, will impute their owne faultes to their neighbour; ſo eaſily they can ſee, ſo exactly diſcuſſe, and ſeuerly cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure their Neighbours defects; but (alas) their owne, they iudge, examine, and behold with the eies of fauour &amp; pittie.</p>
               <p>3. The more Enemies, the more cauſe to be aware, and better knowne; for how many worthies, had ſlept out their liues in obſcurity, had they not beene awaked by <hi>Enmitie? Bias</hi> bids ſo loue
<pb facs="tcp:2942:19"/>our friends, as they may become our foes, which councell, though allowed by many, I like not; for it is the true bane of friendſhip. Therefore, in my hatred, I had rather thinke of loue, then in my loue thinke of hatred; I will not loue ſo, as I may hate; but if I hate, it ſhall be ſo, as I may loue againe. <q xml:lang="lat">Nulla Neceſsitudo eſt, qua non odijs eſſe poſſit infecta; ſola Amicitia ſincera, mali huius ignare eſt: nec magis odioſus Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, quam Amor etiam odioſus.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Pietie to Parents.</head>
               <p>THe fathers hardneſſe, hath often prou'd the ſonnes happineſſe; his tenderneſſe, the others deſtruction.</p>
               <p>2. If you endure a hard father now, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb facs="tcp:2942:20"/>the hard ſonne, he hath ſuffred of you before.</p>
               <p>3 There is no cauſe of a hard ſonnes complaint, againſt his hard father; for hard mettalls are ſooner mollified by their like; and many times, tender-handed Chirurgians leaue the Fouler ſcarres:</p>
               <p>4 Fatherly frownes are lawfully excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by zeale, by Care, by feare, by age.</p>
               <p>5 Of our Parents, wee muſt euer make honorable mention, or none at all.</p>
               <p>6. I muſt neuer iudge of my father, but rather be iudged by him, as the ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary Author of my being: and if he be not capable of true praiſe, I will reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence him with comly ſilence.</p>
               <p>7. There is no power on earth more
<pb facs="tcp:2942:20"/>iuſt, then that of the father ouer the ſonne; nor any ſeruice more honeſt, and due, then that of the ſonne to the father.</p>
               <p>8 If my father be yet liuing, I will ſerue, and attend him with duty, and dilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence; for an olde Father, is a dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Comfort.</p>
               <p>9 My father being old, I had not need to be ydle: therefore, I will be buſie in gathering the laſt fruits of him, as of a falling tree: I will alwaies be as neere him as I can, I will be deſirous to ſee him; as one ready to take his leaue of me, and more deſirous to heare him: his laſt words will I lay vp in the Cloſet of my heart: They will helpe to defend me, in the deſert of this world, for when I would haue his councell, I ſhall ſeeke him, and not finde him at home.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2942:21"/>
               <p> 10 If my father be impotent, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepit, I will tender vnto him the laſt offices of pyety, and ſeruice; for if I omit them now, they will vpbraid me hereafter.</p>
               <p>11 The Fathers loue is great, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vehement: both ſuch, and ſo great as ſcarce any Childes can be equall.
<q xml:lang="lat">Nihil tam ſuum cui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> est, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> filius Pat<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i, nihil cuique in digntus eripitur.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2942:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
